Grand Rapids, Mich. Wallin Congregational Church records, 1896-2016.
Congregational Library & Archives
Grand Rapids, Mich. Wallin Congregational Church records, 1896-2016.
RG5408
Congregational Library & Archives
3.42 Cubic Feet
(5 boxes, 4 reels, 1 folder)
The Lincoln Park Sunday School in Grand Rapids, Michigan, was formed in 1894. The Barker Memorial Branch Church was formed out of the Sunday school in 1896. The church moved locations in 1906 and was renamed to Wallin Congregational Church. The church was remodeled in 1947. The church began searching for land to build a new church in 1958 and that effort was concluded in 1964 when a new church building was constructed. The church remained active in the following decades with a strong focus on local mission work. The church closed in 2019 and donated the church building to the Sudanese Grace Episcopal Church. This collection contains the administrative, building, vital, and photographic records of the Wallin Congregational Church. The collection includes meeting minutes, vital records, fundraising records, blueprints and drawings, programs, and correspondence.
Wallin Congregational Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.)
Barker Memorial Branch Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Wallin Congregational Church in December 2919; 2019-30.
Historical Note
The history of the Wallin Congregational Church began in 1894 with the formation of the Lincoln Park Sunday School. It was formed, in part, by members of the Young People's Society of the South Congregational Church and its first superintendent was Rev. McRoberts of Smith Memorial Church. One of the earliest supporters of the Sunday school was George M. Barker who deeded two lots of land to the school in 1895. On one of those lots, a chapel was built and the chapel was reorganized as the Barker Memorial Branch Church in 1896. Initially the church was a branch of the Park Congregational Church. Due to rapid growth, the church moved to a new location in 1906. The move and expansion of the church building was largely made possible through the donation of money from Van A. Wallin. With the church building's expansion, the church was renamed to Wallin Congregational Church.
The church prospered during the first half of the 20th century. During World War II, the church was used as a training center for Air Raid Wardens and Block Wardens. The church purchased a new organ in 1945 and the church was remodeled in 1947. New pews were installed in 1956. At the same time, the church began to search for land to build a new church to meet the needs of the growing congregation. In 1958 land was purchased for a new church building. The land was paid off in 1960 and construction of the new building was begun in 1962 and completed in 1964. A portion of the land purchased was taken by the state of Michigan as part of the plans of the Highway Department.
The church joined the United Church of Christ in 1961. The church suffered financial difficulties in the late 1960s and 1970s, largely due to extent economic forces. In 1978, the church held a mortgage burning ceremony. The church remained active in the following decades with a strong focus on local mission work. The church closed in 2019 and donated the church building to the Sudanese Grace Episcopal Church.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records of the Wallin Congregational Church from Grand Rapids, Michigan. The records include the church's administrative records, records related to ministers, records related to the church building and land, documents detailing church activities, vital records, and photographic materials. The collection includes meeting minutes, marriage records, baptismal records, memorials, building records, fundraising records, blueprints and drawings, photographs, programs, newsletters, and correspondence.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the five series listed below. Materials within each series have been arranged by chronological order.
Series 1: Administrative records, 1896-2003
Series 2: Audiovisual materials, 1896-2016
Series 3: Church activities, 1906-1990
Series 4: Building records, 1907-1991
Series 5: Membership and vital records, 1937-2014
Content Warning
This collection includes content and language that may be upsetting or triggering. These records reflect the language and attitudes of the historical period in which they were created; many of these terms are unacceptable today. The Congregational Library & Archives works to preserve Congregational history and stories while acknowledging that sometimes that history is problematic or questionable. We do this to preserve, contextualize, and reflect on the past so that we may learn from it.
This collection includes images and language that is racist.
Baptismal records.; Church buildings.; Church bulletins.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Newsletters.; Marriage records.; Photograph albums.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Barker Memorial Branch Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.) -- Church history.; Wallin Congregational Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.)
- Administrative records, 1896 2003; 1896-2003; 6 Volumes; 21 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains church records and records related to the administration of the church. This series also includes records related to the pastorate of the church. The series contains meeting minutes, by-laws and constitutions, legal and insurance records, pastoral committee records and other records related to church ministers, and clerk's records.
  - Church records, 1896 1918; 1896-1918 (Box 1, Volume 1, Folder 1)
  - Pastor's aid society records, 1914 1997; 1914-1919, 1932, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Church records, 1918 1926; 1918-1926 (Box 1, Volume 2, Folder 1)
  - Church records, 1927 1937; 1927-1937 (Box 1, Volume 3, Folder 1)
  - By-laws, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Church records, 1937 1950; 1937-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mortgage records, 1948 1978; 1948-1978 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Church records, 1951 1959; 1951-1959 (Box 1, Volume 4, Folder 1)
  - Pastoral committee, 1953 1963; 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - John C. Whitcomb installation, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - John C. Whitcomb installation and clippings, 1954 1969; 1954-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Board of trustees correspondence, 1955 1967; 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - UCC formation, 1956 1963; 1956-1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous legal records, 1958 1991; 1958-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Church records, 1960 1966; 1960-1966 (Box 1, Volume 5, Folder 1)
  - Name change vote, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Church records, 1966 1978; 1966-1978 (Box 1, Volume 6, Folder 1)
  - Constitutions, 1969 1987; 1969-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Insurance records, 1971 1991; 1971-1991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - John C. Whitcomb 20th anniversary celebration, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - John C. Whitcomb 25th anniversary celebration, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clerk's records, 1986 1992; 1986-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clerk's records, 2002 2003; 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Church profile, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Audiovisual materials, 1896 2016; 1896-2016; 30 Folders; 4 Reels
  This series contains audiovisual materials related to the activities of the members of the Wallin Congregational Church. The series includes photographs, film reels, a video cassette, a photo album, and a scrapbook.
  - Old folks concert, 1896 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - George Washington party, 1902 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chuch dinner photograph, circa 1920 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - "Aunt Samanthy's Album" photograph, circa 1925 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Church building photographs, 1948 1963; 1948-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Unorganized photographs of people, 1950 2000; circa 1950-2000 (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Unorganized photographs of people with labels, 1950 2000; circa 1950-2000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Church choirs, circa 1959 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - New building photographs, circa 1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Confirmation classes, 1963 2006; 1963-2006 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Rev. Wick sermon, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 100th anniversary photograph, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, 2001 2007; 2001-2007, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Polaroids, 2002, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook, 2015 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - 120th anniversary photograph, 2016 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Kodachrome movies, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of military men, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ministers, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Historical photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Missionary society photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Church group photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Marette Fox Hudson portrait, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Halloween party photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Play party photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Sunday school photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Mr. and Mrs. Kettle photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - "Ministers' Honey Moon" photograph, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Photograph album, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Minstrel show photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Wallin church history and movies, undated (Reel 1, Reel 2, Reel 3, Reel 4)
- Church activities, 1906 1990; 1906-1990; 18 Folders
  This series contains records related to the activities of the members of the Wallin Congregational Church. This series includes newsletters, certificates, programs and bulletins, clippings, and correspondence.
  - Dedication services, 1906 1969; 1906-1969 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Newsletters, 1928 1931; 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Opportunity club minstrel show programming, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Certificates, 1933 2018; 1933-2018 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Clippings, 1936 1985; 1936-1985 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 50th anniversary program, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Church histories, 1946 1996; 1946-1996 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Homecoming day, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - 50 year members, 1966 1977; 1966, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Confirmation classes, 1966 1991; 1966-1991 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Church 75th anniversary, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - United States bicentennial celebration, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Mortgage burning, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Inspiration Sunday, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - A day to remember, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miscelaneous correspondence, 1990, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - World War II poem, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Opportunity club cookbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Building records, 1907 1991; 1907-1991; 20 Folders
  This series contains records related to the various church buildings that have housed the Wallin Congregational Church. This series also contains records related to the purchase of new land. This series includes drawings and blueprints, building committee records, fundraising related records, and records related to dedications of church buildings.
  - Miscellaneous building records, 1907 1991; 1907-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Building records and clippings, 1936 1963; 1936-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Parsonage, 1946 1969; 1946-1969 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Building site, 1956 1959; 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Church building drawings, 1958 1966; 1958, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - New church building correspondence, 1958 1963; 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Church building study groups, 1960 1963; 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous building committee records, 1960 1974; 1960-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Building appraisal, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Canvass director's final report, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Building fund canvasing, 1961 1963; 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - State highway commission records, 1961 1965; 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Blueprints and drawings, 1961 1968; 1961-1968 (Folder 3)
  - Highway maps and land purchase, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Building specifications, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Building specifications, 1962 1963; 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Church building dedication, 1962 1964; 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Groundbreaking and cornerstone ceremonies, 1962 1963; 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Real estate aquisition, 1973 1978; 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Membership and vital records, 1937 2014; 1937-2014; 12 Folders
  This series contains vital records and records related to the members of the church. This series includes baptismal records, marriage records, directories and membership lists, and memorials.
  - Baptismal records, 1937 1938; 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Directories, 1941 1999; 1941-1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Memorial fund and book, 1961 1986; 1961-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Membership lists, 1967 1977; 1967-1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Memorial services, 1964 2018; 1964-2018 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Memorial book, 1973 1990; 1973-1990 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Marriage services, 1977 1993; 1977-1993 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Memorial book, 1990 1995; 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Marriage records, 1991 1994; 1991-1994 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Vital records, 1993 2002; 1993-2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Marriage records, 1995 1998; 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Marriage records, 1999 2014; 1999-2014, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)